<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on 2 Cor. 2. XI.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5131B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42862</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875859</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875859</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152401</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93753)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152401)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2257:4d or 2295:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on 2 Cor. 2. XI.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Ralph Simpson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVIII [1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Written by Richard Stafford," -- p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 2295:26 cropped, stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams's Library (London) and Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 2257:4d with: The exceeding great comfort and benefit of having walked before God in truth, and with a perfect heart / by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ... MDCXCIX [1699] -- Sermon I. on Phil. IV. 11 / written by Richard Stafford. [London] : Printed at London, 1698 (Wing S5131C) -- The necessity of keeping still unto the ordinances of religion. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., 1698 (Wing S5126) -- The absolute truth, and utmost certainty of the word of God / by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., MDCXCIX [1699] (Wing S5107F) -- Hear this word, o ye princes, ye priests and people of England. [London : s.n., 1698] (Wing S5120).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, II, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152401:1"/>
            <head>A SERMON On</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 2. XI.</bibl>
                  <p>Leaſt Satan ſhould get an advantage of us, for we are not Ignorant of his devices.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FRom whence we aſſuredly gather, that if St. <hi>Paul,</hi> an Apoſtle and Servant of the Lord, <hi>Who would ſo run, not as at uncertainty;</hi> Who did ſo endeavour, <hi>Leaſt by any means whilſt he had Preached unto others, Himſelf ſhould be a caſt-away,</hi> Spake thus by the Spirit of the Lord, this alſo is written for our Example and Admonition, that every Servant of the Lord who would ſo run his Chriſtian race, not as at uncertainty; Who would ſo wait upon the Lord in all his Ordinances, that after all, he ſhould not prove a caſt-away himſelf (for ſuch a thing is poſſible and to be feared, and care is to be taken againſt it all our Life long.) He ought <hi>not to be Ignorant of the devices of Satan;</hi> for it is certain, the more we know them, the more we may avoid them, or render them of none effect.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>Devices</hi> in the Plural Number; for they are more then one. And indeed it is to be thought, that as <hi>Jeſus asked him what is thy Name, and he ſaid,</hi> Legion, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many Devils were entred into him,</hi> Luke 8. 30. So all his ſeveral <hi>devices</hi> are near upon as many. Now a <hi>Legion</hi> according to that Computation which then was, is Six Thouſand, Six Hundred and Sixty Six; which is a great and conſiderable Number. And if the devices of Satan are ſo many as there are Devils, to treat of them ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and particularly would make a long and perplex Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. I ſhall endeavour to make known unto ye, what I find concerning them in the Book of the Lord, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152401:2"/> to that knowledge himſelf ſhall afford me. All the devices of Satan, may be reduced to theſe two General Heads, or to theſe two Principal Intents and Deſigns which the Enemy of our Souls hath, in uſing his Temptations or Devices againſt us.</p>
            <p>They are either <hi>Firſt,</hi> To hinder People from coming into the way of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Or <hi>Secondly,</hi> To turn them aſide, or back again, after they are come into the way of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In oppoſition unto and prevention of all which, the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God hath two Ends in ſending forth his Word, and in appointing Miniſters for the Miniſtry thereof; which are the <hi>Converting of Sinners from the Errour of their way,</hi> or to bring People over unto God, and then afterwards to <hi>Perſwade them to continue in the Grace of God,</hi> Acts 13. 43. Both which good Ends, do exactly Countermine thoſe two General Devices of Satan afore-mentioned: For God our Saviour would as willingly <hi>have all Men to be ſaved, and to come to the Knowledge of the Truth,</hi> As Satan the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer walketh about as a Roaring Lion, ſeeking whom he may devour; And therefore he endeavours what he can to turn aſide, or hinder People from coming to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth.</p>
            <p>The firſt device of Satan, to hinder People from coming into the way of the Lord and how Contrariwiſe, the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God cryeth out continually unto them to come, we ſhall not here altogether ſo much inſiſt on, (tho' abundance of excellent and uſeful matter might be drawn from thence.) Becauſe it doth not quite ſo cloſely and immediately ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to the Subject in hand, which is the ſecond Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, <hi>Viz. The not being Ignorant how one Principal device of Satan is to turn People aſide, or back again, after they are come into the way of the Lord, is a neceſſary help towards the making a continuing and perſevering work of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid in the true Proverb, <hi>forewarned, fore-armed.</hi> And accordingly, having received notice before hand of ſuch an Enemy or Adverſary; We may expect accordingly and be better provided to withſtand him, or ſo to order our ſelves that his Ends ſhall not be Anſwered upon us. The Great Captain of our ſalvation, the Author and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our Faith, even Chriſt Jeſus hath this manner of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152401:2"/> Speech to his Diſciples and Followers, <hi>Behold I have told you before,</hi> Mat. 24. 25. This he ſpake as to thoſe <hi>Falſe Chriſts and Falſe Prophets, which ſhould ariſe and ſhew Great Signs and Wonders, inſomuch that if it were poſſible, they ſhould deceive the very Elect;</hi> Which hath been lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally fulfilled as to the Falſe Chriſts, and Falſe Prophets of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> For the Prieſts thereof have pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſhew <hi>Great Signs and Wonders</hi> by their forged Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which are recorded in their lying Legends; which have been juſt like a Jugler ſhewing his <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> Tricks, in order to deceive People into their Idolatry, Errour and Superſtition. And all theſe (altho' perhaps themſelves knew it not, or at leaſt they did not throughly conſider thereof) were but Inſtruments in the hands of the Devil, to <hi>deceive the Nations and the World.</hi> Which devices did ſo far take effect, as to deceive the ſimple Multitude of the ſeveral Generations and Countreys; and even to this very Day, they have near upon as many, or rather more in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as the Proteſtants of there formed Religion are. If theſe Poor deluded Souls (whom I Pity at my heart) had kept in mind, or had been acquainted with this Caution of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, then they would not have ſo ſoon fallen into that Deluſion, if they had at all. <hi>But Satan working in them with Greater deceiveablneſs,</hi> kept the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from them; for the way to avoid any Deluſion, which is as a ſnare, is to ſee, or have knowledge of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand. As we have Chriſt for our Lord and Example herein, ſo every Miniſter of Chriſt ought to warn the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and tell them before hand what they will meet with, and what will come upon them in their way towards Heaven, and advertiſe them what ſhall befall them in the latter Days, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 1. For as it is commonly ſaid, If we did know before what would come hereafter, we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do amiſs: So it would be much more as to the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and future things pertaining to the Souls of Men, if they were warned throughly and did receive the warning. When the Watchman ſeeth the Enemy coming, he is to blow the Trumpet and warn the People; according as our God hath commanded and directed us of the Miniſtry, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. And as we come to know the devices of Satan, we are to make them known unto ye alſo.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152401:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>With the well adviſed is Wiſdom.</hi> And People have begun well, when they have reſolved ſo far as this towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as to chooſe it for their Everlaſting and Final abode, and to deſire it for their Habitation. <hi>For the Lord hath choſen Sion, He hath deſired it f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r his Habitation. This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell for I have deſired it,</hi> Pſal. 132. 13, 14. Now <hi>Sion</hi> ſignifies his People: And as there is ſuch a choice, mind and deſire in God towards his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: So it is but Natural and Reaſonable, yea and his Elect Servants have ſuch a reciprocal Love, choice, mind and deſire towards the Lord their God, to be with him wherever he is, rather to be with God in Hell, then to be without him even i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heaven it ſelf, which is an utter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility but even to ſuppoſe; for whereſoever God is, it muſt be Heaven and can be no Hell, <hi>In whoſe preſence is fullneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Joy, and at whoſe right hand are Pleaſures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore;</hi> Like as there muſt be of neceſſity, Light and Heat, in the places next unto where the Sun ſhines.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe, that moſt People are bent for God and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the General, and that they have their <hi>Faces towards Sion.</hi> But I am to acquaint ye, that ſo far it is well, but this will not bring you thither. I mean, the hope to go to Heaven, and ſome Endeavours after it will not give you Footing and Poſſeſſion in that <hi>High and Lofty Place, the Inhabitation of Eternity,</hi> the place where all Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Bleſſedneſs dwells. For who is there in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral that doth not hope to go to Heaven? And doth not uſe ſome endeavours after it. Ye ſhall hardly find one Man or Woman in Twenty, whom if you ask as much, they will tell you the ſame. I do for my part hope to go Heaven, and ſo doth another, yea, and a third, and each doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour ſomewhat after it. For this makes them go to Church or Meeting about once a Month, or once a Quarter, and to carry forth an indifferent outward Moral, Civil and Honeſt Converſation towards one another; for they think this enough to bring them to Heaven, and this is their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after it. As I juſt Name and obſerve this unto ye, Cannot ye ſmell out a <hi>device of Satan</hi> herein? Which may by and by a little appear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hereby he delude and deceives the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ve the turn to bring them to Heaven, then rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152401:3"/>
            <p>I have much Pondered in my heart, upon <hi>Luke 13. 23, 24. Then ſaid one unto him, Lord, Are there few that be ſaved? And he ſaid unto them, ſtrive to enter in at the ſtreight Gate; for many, I ſay unto you will ſeek to enter in and ſhall not be able.</hi> Every ſentence, Word and Syllable, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the very Jota's, or Points in Scripture are obſervable; for it will be all fulfilled and found true in its Seaſon. This I warn ye of conſtantly, and <hi>Behold I have told you before.</hi> In the end of time and in the latter days, when ye ſhall ſtand again on the Earth ye ſhall ſee it in like manner to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and all things to be ſo as is there written. So here it is to be taken notice of, that whereas it is not ſaid, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will ſtrive to enter in and ſhall not be able; for they that ſhall ſtrive will indeed enter in, but many will <hi>ſee</hi> to enter in and ſhall not be able. Which word <hi>ſeek</hi> imports leſſer degree of endeavour then <hi>ſtriving</hi> doth. And ſo God declares himſelf in <hi>Heb. 11. 6. To be a rewarder of them; that diligently ſeek him.</hi> It is not ſaid of them that ſeek him, but of them that <hi>diligently ſeek him.</hi> This Point had need to be well and throughly underſtood; for as to this, is the General deceivableneſs and miſcarriage of the whole World, as to their doing enough to obtain Heaven and Salvation. There is none in this Nation of riper Years and Underſtanding, who hath not heard of it, and there is none who doth not deſire it, becauſe of its Goodneſs and Excellency; and eſpecially, becauſe if they are not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, they muſt go into a worſe place. And there is hardly any but doth ſomething or other towards it; for this makes them go to their ſeveral Congregations and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Worſhip. Now a bare courſe of outward and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary Worſhip and no more, is not ſtriving but ſeeking: But when I ſee them going by Multitudes, ſome to one place and ſome to another, and all will not be ſaved who go to Church or Meeting. This is a thing worth the knowing who the very Perſons will be, and to bring it yet cloſer to my ſelf. <hi>Is it I, that do ſerve God to the ſaving of my Soul?</hi> And another ſhould make the ſame and like application and ſo a third, <hi>That every one of you, do ſhew the ſame diligence to the full aſſurance of hope unto the End;</hi> Till every one of you do uſe the ſame <hi>diligence</hi> which God hath promiſed that he will <hi>Reward;</hi> Till every one of you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152401:4"/> 
               <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtreight Gate.</hi> Striving imports in the Original Word to put forth all the ſtrength; for ſuch ſhall be able. Let any one but do his utmoſt and his beſt for God, and ſuch God will accept off. But this is the fault and failure, that People do not their beſt and their utmoſt for God: Or, if they do it for a Seaſon, yet they do not continue it; and ſo they forfeit their own Share and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Promiſes. The Scripture hath told us before, how it will be divided and rendred to every one at the laſt day; and this doth mention ſeveral who run, but one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the Prize. Of four ſorts of Hearers of the Word, one only bringeth forth Fruit unto Everlaſting Life. <hi>And the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> (which there ſignifies the outward Exhibition, holding forth, or Diſpenſation of the Goſpel) <hi>Is like unto a Not that was caſt into the Sea and gathered of every kind; which when it was full, they drew to the ſhore, and gathered the Good into Veſſels, and caſt the bad away; ſo ſhall it be at the End of the World. The Angels ſhall come forth and ſever the wicked from the juſt,</hi> Mat. 13. 47, 48, 49. We read many ſuch like things there, which declare and ſet forth, how that all will not go to Heaven who talk thereof, or ſomewhat deſire it, or ſlightly endeavour after it. Altho' they herd themſelves amongſt his viſible Church, and frequent his outward Worſhip all their lives long.</p>
            <p>I have often thought as to my ſelf, when I have heard the Good and Eternal things of God declared and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, What do they all ſignify and avail if I ſhould not have an Intereſt and Propriety in them, and if they ſhould not belong to me? When all comes to all, nothing leſs then this will ſuffice me, <hi>To be a Partaker of the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in Light.</hi> This is the thing my Soul craves after, and will never be ſatisfied until it is ſure thereof, as it is continually vexed when ſhe meets with things that croſs, or hinder her in ſeeking and labouring hereafter. As <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Lord ſhew us the Father and it ſufficeth us,</hi> I will be bold here to ſay, that either for God to be ſhewn unto us, as we may ſee him through a Glaſs darkly, of theſe Created things, or as he is ſhewed unto us in the Word Preached, Read, or Heard; This doth not altogether ſo truly, fully and throughly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152401:4"/> the Soul of Man, altho' it doth a little more when in Truth, and in an inward Witneſſing it can ſay, <hi>My Lord, and my God,</hi> by way of Propriety and Claiming him to ones ſelf. And yet here again, becauſe here there may be ſome doubt and further thought of Soul, nothing leſs can ſatisfy the Soul of Man, then for her to enjoy God in Heaven. And ſo it is here aforeſaid, <hi>That the Lord hath choſen Zion,</hi> which ſignifies his People, <hi>This is my reſt for ever; here will I dwell for I have deſired it,</hi> which implies an Union to him. So the Language of the Creature ſpeaks again unto him, <hi>As the heart panteth after the Water Brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee O God. My Soul Thirſteth for God, for the living God, when ſhall I come and appear before God,</hi> Pſal. 42. 1, 2. It is evident, that the Soul hath a Natural deſire to know God, not in thoſe who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced it with Senſuality and Brutiſhneſs. Not in thoſe who are <hi>Alienated and Enemies through wicked works,</hi> but in them who exert the Operations thereof. Who obey and ſerve their Creator, even as it is meet and right that his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhould do. So when the Soul comes to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him, ſhe is in Peace. It can be contented for the preſent, and wait ſome time for the full Enjoyment of him; Altho' in this mean while, the <hi>Earneſt Expectation of the Creature waiteth for the Manifeſtation of the Sons of God.</hi> There are riſings in the Souls of Men and Women (a little imperfect meaſure whereof, they have in this Life towards Communion and Union with their God. As alſo becauſe we are given to underſtand, that many will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and caſt off from him at the laſt day, altho' they were his Creatures and the work of his hands, hence doth ariſe <hi>Great Thought and Searching of Heart,</hi> leaſt we ſhould be of the Number of them.</p>
            <p>Well, to help and remedy that, to Encourage People to ſhew the ſame diligence unto the full aſſurance of hope un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the End, I do here make known unto ye, that the ſure way to obtain is to have <hi>Faith in God, and to Love him with all our Heart, and with all our Soul, and with all our Strength, and with all our Mind.</hi> There is all the Reaſon in the World that he ſhould be ſo loved and ſerved. Never any one that did thus believe and love and ſerve him, did Finally and Eternally Periſh. <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed came on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152401:5"/> Mount <hi>Piſgah.</hi> He ſaw an Earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> and never came into it, but now he is in a much better, <hi>Viz.</hi> The Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men may be and are diſappointed in their Purſuits after Earthly things, altho' they uſed Diligence and Wiſdom, and were ready to lay hold on them. But none that doth ſo as to Heaven, who hath the <hi>Hope which enters within the vail,</hi> and ſuch a ſight thereof as to overlook preſent things, who takes up this firm, conſtant and continued reſoluti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, for that will I labour and care all the Days of this Life of Vanity. Whatever I take in hand, or whatever my hand finds me to do, I will bring it all in tendency, ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſubſerviency thereto, or otherwiſe I will never do it: None ſuch who do thus, ſhall miſs thereof. <hi>Be ye ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, for as much as ye know, that your Labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> Here again obſerve, it is called <hi>Labour;</hi> for this imports a great deal more then that careleſs and cuſtomary Religion of the Multitude. But when it is made a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Striving,</hi> and it becomes the conſtant and only buſineſs of all our Life long; When the <hi>Life which we live is by Faith in the Son of God,</hi> That is, when that Faith doth ſo actuate us throughly and wholly, all one, as the Soul doth actuate the Body in order to Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Life, to ſuch the Word and Promiſe of God, ſtands en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, that they <hi>Shall not Labour in vain, nor yet ſeek his Face in vain;</hi> But they ſhall obtain that which they ſeek after, <hi>viz.</hi> The Enjoyment of God, and a Manſion in their Fathers Houſe in the higheſt Heavens.</p>
            <p>It is a great and obſervable Scripture, <hi>Iſrael hath not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that which he ſeeketh for, but the Election hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, and the reſt are blinded,</hi> Rom. 11. 7.</p>
            <p>There is many ſuch a thought in Godly and Gracious Souls, like unto that of <hi>David,</hi> who after that, he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Promiſe of being King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> could ſay, <hi>I ſhall fall one day by the hands of Saul.</hi> And ſo to whom <hi>pertaineth the Adoption, the Covenants, and the Promiſes;</hi> Yet there is in them a ſecret diſtruſt and miſ-giving of heart, I ſhall fall one day into the Paws of the Roaring Lion, who walketh about continually, ſeeking whom he may devour. Notwithſtanding, I have already done and yet do ſo much in order to God, I may be a caſt-away for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152401:5"/> all that. Indeed there may be ſome good uſe of ſuch kind of Thoughts, to keep us always on our watch, <hi>That we may not be high minded, but fear; and to work out our own ſalvation with fear and trembling; and there being a promiſe left us o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> entring into his reſt, to fear, leaſt any of us ſhould come ſhort of it.</hi> And as when <hi>David</hi> ſpake thus of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in reference to <hi>Saul,</hi> he did all that ſame time endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to flee from, avoid and fortify himſelf againſt <hi>Saul.</hi> So tho' we have at ſome times doubtful thoughts, leaſt he ſhould prevail and get an advantage over us, at the ſame time, <hi>we do not give place to the Devil,</hi> Eph. 4. 27. <hi>We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Devil and he will flee from us,</hi> James 4. 7. Then there can be no Great matter of Inconvenience, (but rather good doth ariſe thereby) in thinking the worſt as long as, we act to the beſt in avoiding and arming our minds againſt his Temptations. We had need be upon our continual Watch and Guard, <hi>Be ſober, be vigilant, becauſe your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary the Devil, as a Roaring Lion walketh about, ſeeking whom he may devour, whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith.</hi> He is more cunning then any of us, and holds almoſt all Men and Women by one catch or another, either in the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſome ſin, or in the Omiſſion of ſome Duty, or to tempt them to leave off from their waiting and cloſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering unto the Lord. <hi>Now the Serpent was more ſubtle then any Beaſt of the Field, which the Lord God had made.</hi> Mark that well, and ſo he continues at this day to be more ſubtle then any Man or Woman conſidered in their meer Natural condition, abſtracted and ſeparated from the aſſiſtances above, the Directions of the Word and Spirit. And ſo he purſues near the ſame methods, ſtill to tempt and deceive all Mankind of all Generations and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, as He ſeduced our firſt Parents into the Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the ſame may be read throughout, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. Even to tempt and beguile them into the Breach, of as many of the Commandments as ever he can, with a pretence that leſs Evil and more ſeeming Good, will enſue thereupon then really will. He ſuggeſts to do any thing that may diſpleaſe and loſe the favour of God; and by conſequence fall under his wrath and future Puniſhment. Theſe and ſuch like things are obvious and commonly known already. And ſo where we Read in ſeveral places of Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152401:6"/> the <hi>Serpent, Satan,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>Adverſary,</hi> the <hi>Evil one,</hi> the <hi>Great Dragon;</hi> All this is commonly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in very plain Words that any one may underſtand, that it is all meant and intended of him. For whoſoever hath conſtant Recourſe unto the written Word of God and doth read diligently therein, he will not be Ignorant of the Devices of Satan. Thus <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Chriſtians of his time came not to be Ignorant of the Devices of Satan, as indeed there are ſo many things ſcattered up and down therein which are ſpoken concerning them, that whoſo readeth will quickly find them. <hi>And the Great Dragon was caſt out, the Old Serpent, called the Devil and Satan, which deceiveth the whole World, he was caſt out into the Earth. Therefore rejoyce ye Heavens and ye that dwell in them. Wo, to the Inhabitants of the Earth and of the Sea, becauſe the Devil is come down unto you, having great wrath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe be knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> Rev. 12. 9, 12. <hi>And deceiveth them that dwell on the Earth,</hi> Rev. 13. 14. <hi>And theſe are they by the way ſide, where the word is ſown, but when they have heard Satan cometh immediately, and taketh away the word that was ſown in their hearts,</hi> Mark 4. 15. Not to multiply many more Texts to the ſame purpoſe, we may find and feel enough of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſuggeſtions of Satan within our ſelves. When at any time we are kept off, hindred and neglect any good, It is commonly through this Temptation and Inſtigation of the Evil one; as alſo he doth miſerably perplex and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in the things pertaining to God. <hi>Simon, Simon, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath deſired to ſift thee as Wheat, but I have prayed that thy faith fail not, and when thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren.</hi> Now this <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> was a Diſciple and Precious Servant of Jeſus Chriſt; and from thence we ſee, that Satan is as buſy with the Children and Servants of God, as with other People. Yea, rather more in that, he hath already taken the others Captive at his Will. And hereby alſo we are given to underſtand, that God hath reſerved to himſelf the Power over him. He can go no further then God ſuffers and permits. Tho' Satan for theſe Five or Six Thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ears, hath been let looſe among the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth, yet God can tye him up again whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he will; and he doth walk about with a hook in his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152401:6"/> Jaws to be turned back, or about, whither ſoever doth pleaſe the Great Creator of all things. <hi>But I know thy abode and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy Rage againſt me; Becauſe thy rage againſt me, and thy tumult is come up into my Ears, therefore will I put my Hook in thy Noſe, and my Bridle in thy Lips, and I will turn thee back by the way, by which thou cameſt,</hi> Iſa. 37. 28, 29. Holds equally true of the infernal accurſed Spirit himſelf, as it did of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> or <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> through whom he Acted. For every Man is Acted either by God or the Devil, according as the thing which he doth, is Good or Evil, Lawful and Right, or elſe ſin: And ſo it is of all the Created things they have but a ſtinted and limited Commiſſion and Power given to them by the Great and Sovereign Creator of all things, whither they do obey, or Act in Rebellion againſt him; Both which will tend to the Great Ends of his own Glory. God hath ſuffered ſuch an Infernal and Inviſible Spirit, as the Devil or Satan is, to prove the Children of Men more perfectly, to know what is in their heart, whither they will keep his Commandments or no. That according as it is written, <hi>He that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill; and he that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill; and He that is Holy, let him be Holy ſtill,</hi> Rev. 22. 11. <hi>But the wicked ſhall do wickedly, and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand,</hi> Dan. 12. 10. So theſe things ſeem to be ſuffered, ſo on ſet purpoſe, that they which are good may be better, and ſo may have more favour from God, and a greater reward to themſelves; and the bad may be worſe, and conſequently be beaten with more ſtripes, and receive yet a greater Condemnation. This laſt ſeems to be an hard ſaying, but it is according to the order and decree of God, and according to the Scriptures of Truth. It is evident by the Example and Hiſtory of <hi>Job,</hi> particularly in the firſt and ſecond Chapters, that by there being a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and by his being permitted to afflict the Body and Tempt his Soul; The Good and Righteous are hereby proved, and they will have yet more favour and a greater Crown from the Lord, who ſuffered it ſo to be, that the <hi>Trial of their Faith being much more Precious then of Gold that Periſheth, might be found unto Praiſe and Honour and Glory, at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> When this <hi>Job</hi> was proved, he did approve himſelf unto God. What an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152401:7"/> Character is that left recorded of him? That amidſt his very Great Afflictions and Troubles, <hi>In all this</hi> Job <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, nor charged God Fooliſhly.</hi> And how comfortable is that after all, <hi>And the Lord tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned the Captivity of</hi> Job: <hi>Alſo the Lord gave</hi> Job <hi>twice as much as he had before. So the Lord bleſſed the latter end of</hi> Job, <hi>more then the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> Hereby Confirming what he after<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ards ſpoke by his Apoſtle <hi>James, Behold we count them happy which endure. Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have heard of the Patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and have ſeen the End of the Lord, that the Lord is very Pitiful and of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy,</hi> James 5. 11. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that endureth Temptation, for when he is tried, he ſhall receive the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that Love him,</hi> James 1. 12. Happy was it for <hi>Job,</hi> that ever there was a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tan to torment him; though perhaps himſelf could not think ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the very Inſtant, <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r no Chaſtening, for the preſent ſeemeth Joyous but Grievous; Nevertheleſs, afterward it yeildeth the Peaceable Fruits of Righteouſneſs unto them which are Exerciſed thereby,</hi> Heb. 12. 11. For it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made double to him in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Life, and much more will be added unto him in the reſtitution of all things.</p>
            <p>Indeed it muſt be acknowledged, to ſpeak as a Man, that no one who did throughly conſider of things, would chooſe to bear Afflictions, Trouble, or Loſs in his Youth, or in the foregoing time of his Life, if he was ſure to have towards his latter days, double, or two fold, as much for the loſs he ſuſtained. For Fifty Pounds a Year in Youth, is better then an hundred in declining Years or Old Age, not only becauſe of what <hi>Barvillai</hi> ſaid, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not then ſo well taſte what we Eat or Drink But admit that did remain, yet it is leſſened again by having had it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo very often. But the chief Reaſon is, becauſe of the nearer, yea, the very near approaches of Death; which then doth caſt an Allay, and damp, even upon all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Pleaſures and Lawful Comforts of Life. Which is one Reaſon why this Age, unleſs it is attempered with Grace and Knowledge, is commonly ſo fretful, vaſpiſh and froward. But God having here promiſed a <hi>Crown of Life, to the enduring of Temptation unto ſuch as Love him</hi> (which at this day is made good unto his Servant <hi>Job;</hi> for as <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> do live unto God, ſo doth his Soul alſo at this very moment ſomewhere exiſt)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152401:7"/> this doth mightily alter the Caſe, and make thoſe Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to be willingly ſubmitted unto; Yea, to become a matter of choice (I had rather meet with trouble in the way of Duty, then to avoid it in the neglect and omiſſion thereof) when theſe temptations do tend and work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our Endleſs Good in the latter End; and herein is that ſaying true, <hi>It is Good for a Man that he bear his Yoke in his Youth,</hi> Lam. 3. 27. This is a mighty Word of Conſolation to me, who have born the Yoke to a Witneſs in my Youth, whoſe Life from my Youth up, hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a continued train and ſeries of Afflictions; and I do ſtill labour under Croſſes, Oppoſitions, Diſappointments, Vexations and Oppre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſions. Tho' withal, (Bleſſed be his Name for it.) My God hath given me that Knowledge to eye and diſcern therein, ſomewhat more then the firſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hand, or next viſible Inſtrument therein. For as it is Written, <hi>The Prophet is a Snare of the Fowler in his ways,</hi> Hoſ. 9. 8. So I look upon thoſe Temptations as a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are of the Great Fowler, for the Souls of Men. And as it is again written, <hi>Our Soul is eſcaped as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowler, the Snare is broken and we are eſcaped,</hi> Pſal. 1 24. 7. So thoſe Temptations and Snares, may at firſt be many times ſeen, and ſo paſſed by or avoided; or if one falls unawares into them, or if like Troops of numerous Enemies, they do come and beſet one round, by the help and Grace of God we may reſolutely break through and not be holden by them. We may work through or over, or by the rub and hindrance, ſo as not to be let thereby: Tho' we may be ſomewhat hindred, yet not utterly ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. It is not ſo much the Children of Men, or our Fellow Creatures which do tempt or torment us, but it is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil who Acts through them (from whence, Note by the way, that either to tempt or occaſion another to ſin, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comes ſo like unto the Nature of the Devil as this doth; as alſo it is ſomewhat like him to Vex, Diſquiet, or Torment, only for Vexation ſake as we commonly ſay.) The Devil is the Great Inſtrument or Engine, which ſets all the Sin and Evil, all the Temptations and Pain a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or in Motion, as it hath been and is in the World. Here God doth ſuperintend and over-rule all, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, or ſuffers him to Act according to his own Will and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152401:8"/> Pleaſure. <hi>Behold I have Created the waſter to deſtroy,</hi> Iſa. 54. 6. Which <hi>waſter</hi> to deſtroy is the Devil; for he doth raiſe and occaſion all thoſe Deſtructions, for they do Spring up from him, as the black and corrupt Fountain that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath. Somewhat hereof is ſignified by what our Saviour Chriſt ſaith unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> I am from above, and ye are from beneath. <hi>Ye are of your Father the Devil, and the Luſts of your Father ye will do,</hi> (Obſerve how it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Plural Number, <hi>Luſts,</hi> more then one; as alſo we hence ſee that all Luſt comes under, and is ſome of the Devices of Satan) <hi>He was a Murderer from the beginning,</hi> John 8. 44. There are ſeveral ſorts of Luſts, ſome of which do immediately tend to Fighting and Murder; and the others do weaken and tend to deſtroy. He hath his Name in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue, <hi>Abaddon,</hi> but in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue hath his Name <hi>Apollyon,</hi> Rev. 9. 11. Which in the Margent of the Bible there is, That is to ſay, <hi>A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it is to be underſtood, that the Devil was a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture made by God, as may be gathered from <hi>John 1. 3. Col. 1. 16. Iſa.</hi> 54. 16. He is the <hi>Great waſter that was Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to deſtroy.</hi> Like as the fire was Created to burn as well as to warm, ſo that Infernal Spirit was Created to deceive and puniſh the Children of the Kingdom and thoſe that does Iniquity, all one, as to prove and try the Servants of the Lord. He hath been ſuffered to have his Range, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about ſeeking whom he may devour, and whom he may deſtroy; To deceive the Nations and the whole World, both as taken together and alſo in their ſingle Individual Perſons. <hi>And the Devil ſaid unto Chriſt, All this Power will I give thee, for that is delivered unto me,</hi> Luke 4. 6. By whom muſt this be delivered unto him, but by the Great Creator and Maker of all things, who is God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? We read expreſly and clearly in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> how that Power is given unto them to do ſo far and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as to one of his Angels, to <hi>take Peace off from the Earth,</hi> and many ſuch like things. By which it may be eaſily underſtood and conceived, how that even now God is All in All. As he hath Created all things by his Great Power and Wiſdom, ſo He that <hi>rideth upon the Heavens, by his Name,</hi> Jah, Pſal. 68. 4. Doth keep the Reins ſtill in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152401:8"/> his hands, and let them go, or ſtops, or turns them as himſelf pleaſes. This was hinted off before, but it is ſafe to mention it again, that ye be not Ignorant of the devices of Satan, how far they go and no further, for even as he hath put Bounds to the Sea, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou go and no further, and here thy Proud Waves are ſtayed.</hi> So it is as to the devices of Satan, and what is conſequent to them, the Wickedneſs, Oppoſition, or Rebellion of Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And after theſe things, I ſaw four Angels ſtanding at the four Corners of the Earth, holding the four Winds of the Earth, that the Wind ſhould not blow on the Earth, nor on the Sea, nor on any Tree. And I ſaw another Angel aſcending from the</hi> Eaſt, <hi>having the Seal of the living God; and He cried with a loud Voice to the four Angels, to whom it was given.</hi> (Mark that, for unleſs, God had given them the Power, they could no more hurt them, then I ſitting here can hurt the Scaly <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that is at the bottom of the Sea.) <hi>To hurt the Earth and the Sea, ſaying, hurt not the Earth, neither the Sea, nor the Trees, till we have Sealed the Servants of God in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oreheads,</hi> Rev. 7. 1, 2, 3. <hi>And it was Commanded them that they ſhould not hurt the Graſs of the Earth, neither any green thing, neither any Tree; but only thoſe Men which have not the Seal of God in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads,</hi> Rev. 9. 4. From whence we ſee, that all the Actings and Temptations, and Devices of Satan, who is <hi>Belzebub,</hi> the Prince of the Devils; Yea, all the things in the whole World cannot hurt any one, unleſs God hath before given him Commiſſion and Power, or leave to hurt; as again here we read, That the Servants of God who have his Seal in their Foreheads, are priviledged and exempted from being hurt. For nothing can truly hurt them, not Pain, nor Sickneſs, nor Poverty, nor yet Death it ſelf; for that only brings them to God whoſe Seal they before had. This is the Heritage of the Servants of the Lord, that they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his Protection always about them; not in their Pockets, for they may be ſtript Naked and then it might be taken from them, but in their Foreheads, which is not ſeen by Mans Eye: So that no Power, or Malice of Men can defeat or annull it. Which. Protection runs in this form of Words. <hi>Behold I give unto you Power to tread on Serpents and Scorpions, and over all the Power of the Enemy, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152401:9"/> nothing ſhall by any means hurt you,</hi> Luke 10. 19. Nothing throughout the whole Creation, can by any means hurt the Diſciples and Servants of Chriſt. No not the Devils, nor yet Death it ſelf can hurt them, but ſin only. The Devil can no otherwiſe hurt any one whatever, but as he doth tempt and deceive them into ſin; and then indeed it is, that he gets advantage over them and his devices take ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. But as long as any one doth <hi>not defile his Garments,</hi> Rev. 3. 4. Or as long as he ſtands upon the Watch, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or at ſtaves End. Avoid, or get behind me Satan, here let Satan do his worſt and ſhew his utmoſt cunning, it ſignifies not. It is Good and Prudent counſel never to ſtand Parlying, or Diſcourſing with him, for thus he led our firſt Parents into the Tranſgreſſion. But rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt vigorouſly and he will flee from us, and break through the Hoſt of theſe Helliſh Enemies. The more he tempts and the more often we come off Conquerours, the greater will be our Triumph and Crown, and Joy, in the Day of the Lord. For as before remarked of <hi>Job,</hi> happy it was for him, that there was ever a Devil to have tempted him. So the ſame will be returned and found true of all the other Servants and Children of God, they will be pronounced and rendred bleſſed, that ever they have endured Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for then they were tried. But now they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crown of Life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him, who in his Gracious, Wonderful and Over-ruling Providence (which ſignifies providing or ordaining of things) <hi>Will make all things work together for Good to them that Love God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he ſhewed me</hi> Joſhua <hi>the High Prieſt, ſtanding before the Angel of the Lord, and Satan ſtanding at his right hand to reſiſt him,</hi> Zech. 3, 1. So <hi>Paul</hi> Witneſſeth, he would have come to ſome he wrote unto, but Satan hindred him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain he expreſſeth it on this wiſe, <hi>Only he who now letteth, will let until he be taken out of the way,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 7. From all which we gather, that all reſiſtances, hindrances and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in the things that are Good, or for God; They do come and ariſe from Satan, and here we ſhould reſiſt the reſiſtance (which is ſignified by that Phraſe of the Pſalmiſt afore-mentioned, <hi>The Snare is broken and we are delivered)</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152401:9"/> and ſo not ſuffer our ſelves to be hindred by the hindrance (for I am pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſwaded and do believe, that if <hi>Paul</hi> had been throughly bent and reſolved on it for all, he might have went that Journey; Notwithſtanding the hindrance of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. As a Man may ſuffer himſelf to be holden by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle thred or tow, if he doth ſomewhat yeild himſelf. The Devils Power is ſo weak and limited, that if we do reſiſt and not give way, not yet yeild ſomewhat our ſelves; he can never have the Maſtery, or Prevalency over us. <hi>Give the Devil his due,</hi> and let none blame him too much nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as to ſay, he doth this or that ſin, or miſchief, when Men and Women do it by Inſtigation of him. For as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Every Man is tempted when he is led away of his own luſt and enticed:</hi> So when any are Tempted, or Inſtigated by the Devil to commit a ſin, the fault and failure of the reaſonable Creatures is this, that themſelves do yeild and conſent to do what he ſuggeſts unto them. Which laſt being their own Act and Deed, thereupon the future Puniſhment of God upon them for the ſame is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and juſtly founded. So it will be as to the final Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage and Condemnation of them at the laſt. <hi>Their Deſtruction is of themſelves,</hi> although they were <hi>ſnared in it as Birds that were caught in a Snare, Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 12. by that great Fowler which hath his Name in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue <hi>Abaddon,</hi> and in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue <hi>Apollyon,</hi> which in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue ſignifies a <hi>Deſtroyer.</hi> Birds and Fiſhes have that little Inſtinct, that if they ſee a Snare, Hook, or Net, they will not willingly ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be caught and taken in it. Even ſo all the Sons of Men have a Rumour of thoſe Evils of the Inviſible World, how, <hi>Fear, and the Pit, and the Snare are upon them, O ye Inhabitants of the Earth!</hi> And they might have that Faith, Knowledge and Reaſon as to foreſee thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and avoid them. But if they put off, and neglect hearing the Word, whereby Faith cometh; if they will not Exerciſe and Improve their Knowledge and Reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſpiritual and future things: When they are given to underſtand, and they may perceive from within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that there is a Devil who tempts and would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, but themſelves give way and conſent unto it. All this is their own fault and wilfulneſs, for which they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152401:10"/> will at laſt ſmart and be puniſhed, be Deſtroyed and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh. <hi>O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, but in me is thy help,</hi> Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 13. 9. And ſo God is an effectual help unto his Creatures, againſt that and other Enemies of their Souls by his Word. Which if we have recourſe unto, we ſhall not be Ignorant of his devices, by that Grace, Knowledge and Aſſiſtance which he gives, offers and tenders unto all. There are ſo many Arguments, Motives and Perſuaſives, to bring Mankind to God and Good things, that whoſo doth attend unto and conſider of them, they muſt needs prevail with ſuch a Soul. There is certainly ſome ſecret Enemy of Mankind whom they ſee not, that keeps them off from God and Good things, and ſeduces them to Evil. Men would never do thus of themſelves, but that an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen Enemy doth ſtir them up. Like as it is recorded, <hi>But there was none like unto</hi> Ahab, <hi>which did ſell himſelf to work wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord, whom</hi> Jeſabel <hi>his Wife did ſtir up,</hi> 1 Kings 21. 25. In the Margent it is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited.</hi> So tho' there is a great deal of Wickedneſs in the heart of Man, by Reaſon of Original and Inbred Corruption <hi>(For the heart is deſperately wicked, Who can know it?)</hi> Yet this Corrupt Nature would never proceed ſo far, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Rebellion againſt and deſpiſing of God, unleſs this Infernal <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> whoſe right Name is <hi>Belzebub,</hi> did ſtir them up. Here again, People might chooſe whether they would; Yea, they might refuſe to be ſtirred up, or Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by him. As the Commandments of God run both ways, <hi>Ceaſe to do Evil, Learn to do well:</hi> So the devices of Satan are contrariwiſe both ways, to tempt the Sons of Men to all the Evil he can, and that they omit or neglect to do well, his devices tend either towards the Commiſſion of Sin, or the Omiſſion of Good. I have ſeveral times ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that at Godly Duties, either Prayer, or hearing the Word, amidſt them there have fallen out Accidents and Caſualties, which then occaſion Diſtraction, Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Hindrance, more then at other times. In a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where hath been Infants and little Children, there hath been more unquietneſs and trouble, when the People have been waiting on the Lord in Religious Exerciſes then at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times. (For which reaſon, when <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſpeak as a Man throughout, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. He rather adviſes not to Marry,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152401:10"/> 
               <hi>That ye may attend upon the Lord without Distraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo the ſame is too often ſeen and experienced, that there is more Hatred, Reproach, rancour and oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſound Preaching, then there is againſt a dead and dull Miniſtry. There is much more of the Serpentine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhewed forth againſt the Power of Godlineſs, then is againſt the form and outſide thereof. Here Satan hath Great wrath and ſhews his Teeth where he cannot Bite, (for God hath limited and chained him) where he ſees (as that Infernal Spirit ſees and diſcerns more then we in the Fleſh do) any thing that would deſtroy or leſſen his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom here on Earth. One ſaid concerning my ſelf, <hi>That Satan had a great Wrath againſt me, becauſe I had a Zeal for God, and would ſeek to overthrow his Kingdom of Darkneſs.</hi> The Truth of which obſervation I have indeed felt and experienced; For I have gone through almoſt all the Shame and Indecencies which are incidental to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, whilſt I was in the courſe of my Miniſtry, which was as much carried on by Writing and Publiſhing, as by Preaching with a lively Voice. <hi>When thou madeſt us a reproach to our Neighbours, a ſcorn and deriſion to them that were round about us. My Confuſion was continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, and the ſhame of my Face did cover me, for the Voice of him that Reproacheth and Blaſphemeth. All this is come upon us, yet have we not forgotten thee, neither have we dealt falſly in thy Covenant; (But we have only aſſerted thy Commandments in the very ſame manner as thou haſt given them,</hi> and they ſtand Written and Recorded for us.) <hi>Tho' thou hast ſore broken us in the place of Dragons, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us with the ſhadow of Death,</hi> Pſal. 44. 13, 14, 15, 16, 18, 19. <hi>When thou haſt laid me in the loweſt Pit, in darkneſs and in the deeps: Thy wrath lieth hard upon me, and thou haſt afflicted me with all thy Waves,</hi> Pſal. 88. 6, 7. Here the Pſalmiſt aſcribes them higher then to Satan the Engine of Torment and Perſecution, who Acts it forth by Incarnate and Viſible Inſtruments, even to God himſelf. But as it is elſewhere Written, <hi>Both</hi> Herod <hi>and</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>with the Gentiles and People of</hi> Iſrael <hi>were gathered together, for to do whatever thy hand and thy Counſel deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined before to be done,</hi> Acts 4. 27, 28. So the Devil and his Legions, and all thoſe People in the Fleſh, Our Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152401:11"/> Creatures, they are all but Inſtruments in the Hand of God, (for the Devil Acted through <hi>Saul</hi> in Perſecuting <hi>David,</hi> and through <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> in putting Chriſt to Death) <hi>For to do whatever thy hand and thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel determined before, or ſuffered to be done.</hi> And ſo I look upon all thoſe Afflictions, Trials and Temptations, which have befaln me. As in Good things, It is not ſuch a Man, but Chriſt which dwelleth in him, who doth the ſame So in Evil things the Devil Acts through them who do Evil. And over and above all things, we may look up unto the Great God. Who over-rules and determines all for the Great Ends of his own Glory. This ſame Truth is now taken notice of a third time, that ye may underſtand it aright, and throughly, and bear and remember it in mind.</p>
            <p>We ſhould endeavour and order things that our <hi>Prayers be not hindred,</hi> which is done by Roving and Wandring Thoughts in them, as they are ſuggeſted by the tempter, who is then buſy to ſpoil and render them of none effect. I have ſeveral times apprehended and concluded, that this device muſt be from Satan the Enemy; and where he would hinder, this muſt be ſome good thing, which would have the favour and acceptance of God if it was not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; and thereupon it muſt be Godly Diſcretion and Soul ſaving Wiſdom, to endeavour as much as you can to the contrary, that your Prayers be not hindred. But attend more diligently on the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me; and ſee to it well, that it doth become an <hi>effectual ſervent Prayer which availeth much.</hi> So it is likewiſe in the hearing of the Word. Satan tryes and endeavours to hinder your hearing. How many doth he hinder from coming to the place of hearing, by putting this little thing, or that little thing into their hearts, either by way of excuſe, or obſtinate refuſal againſt it? Some vain or falſe Imagination. And again, thoſe who come to hear, Do they attend upon the Lord, and upon the Miniſtry of his Word without diſtraction? Do not ſome other Objects, or Thoughts, or Obſervations, take them off at the very time? <hi>Do they give the more earneſt heed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the things which they have heard, lest at any time they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould let them ſlip?</hi> This is the very reaſon, why I do not quote the Chapter and Verſe of many Scriptures, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152401:11"/> whilſt People look after them, they let ſlip many other Sentences of Truth which follow in the courſe of our Preaching. So that either I ſhould make a ſtop or Pauſe hereupon, or I could ſhew ye rather a more excellent and compendious way, then by turning to it in your Bibles, or folding down the leaves. Bring rather a Pen, Ink and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or a Pencil Book; And ſet down only the Chapter and Verſe of every material Proof, and then turn to them when ye come home, which will refreſh and bring it again to your memories, as ye do Recollect what Truth was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, when ſuch a Text of Scripture was alledged. But People are aſhamed to write after the Preacher, and it is not now in Faſhion; but away with that ſhame which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Godly Edifying. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Satan hinders before hearing and in the midſt of hearing, ſo he doth hinder after hearing, <hi>When they have heard, Satan cometh immediately and taketh away the Word that was ſown in their hearts,</hi> Mark 4. 15. As he doth by your falling to worldly talk, or buſineſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently afterwards. Which is juſt like going from a good fire, into the cold open Air in the Winter time. They do not long retain the heat of the fire, but they are again as chilly and as cold as ever. And ſo when ſome have been warmed and heated at this ordinance of hearing the word, they are preſently Lukewarm or ſtark cold again. <hi>Satan cometh immediately and taketh away the word that was ſown in their hearts:</hi> When they only paſs their Opinions, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Verdict upon the Preacher, as if there was no more in a Sermon then to juſt ſit it out, paſs their ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon it afterwards and there is an End. How many of the common People will give ſuch a general Report, that good things were ſpoken off, and it was all very good and the like; but they cannot remember and carry away diſtinctly, not ſo much as one good thing which was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpoken of. Whereas if the very ſame Perſons were at the hearing a Play, Ballad, News, or Story concerning their Neighbours, they could bring away the ſence of that. The heart of ſuch People is juſt like a ſieve, which lets through the Pure, Solid and Subſtantial Grain, and they retain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a little duſt or chaff. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſo on the other hand when they find fault with, or diſlike a Sermon; It is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral again, I do not like, becauſe I do not like it. But they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152401:12"/> cannot aſſign any particular Reaſon thereof; or if they can, it is ſuch a Reaſon that they are aſhamed to own and ſpeak out, becauſe perhaps their Conſciences were touched to the quick by that <hi>Word which is Quick and Powerful ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then any two Edged Sword, Piercing even to the dividing aſunder of Soul and Spirit and of the Joynts and Marrow, and it is a diſcerner of the Thoughts and Intents of the heart:</hi> But Sinners and Hypocrites, and formal Chriſtians do not like ſuch kind of Sermons.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Since ye ſeek a Proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in me,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 3. And ſo he writes unto <hi>Timothy, Make full Proof of thy Miniſtry,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 5. So I would to God, that ye my hearers may find the Proof of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in your ſelves, if this ſame <hi>Miniſtry to you ward is not weak, but mighty in you:</hi> Judge ye in your ſelves, if at this my ſpeaking and propoſing it unto ye, it hath a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble operation and working upon your Hearts and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, this is a Proof and an Evidence, and a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I am inwardly ordained and appointed, and ſent by God for the work of the Miniſtry. Tho' ſome, as <hi>tho' living in the World are Subject unto Ordinances,</hi> Col. 2. 20. Have ſeveral times objected to me, that I do not come in regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>after the Law of a Carnal Commandment;</hi> which doth impoſe and require ſeveral things of Mans deviſing, which God and Chriſt have not required in their Goſpel. And therefore it would be ſin, or doubt of mind in me to comply therewith. If ſuch would come to hear, they would perhaps find a Proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in me; and that is ſufficient to qualify any one for a Miniſter of the Goſpel. But as we are to give a Proof of our Miniſtry, ſo I would willingly ſeek a Proof of my Miniſtry in ye. This ſhall be the Proof my Miniſtry which I would ſeek of ye. How much do ye remember of the ſeveral Sermons I have Preached unto ye? But if ye have for the time paſt remembred but little (I am afraid ſo) I will now put ye in mind of a way that ye may remember more. When thou comeſt home to thy Chamber or Cloſet, then write down as much obſervable Truth as ever thou canſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member. Truly, this was my manner in my Youth; I did ſeldom write after Miniſters, but in the time of my Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Zeal this I would do (which ſame Youthly Zeal ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152401:12"/> be ſtill retained and practiſed.) As when a Man hath been abroad receiving Money, the firſt thing he doth after he comes home is to ſee that it be right, and then he goes and locks it up ſure. So after I had been hearing a Sermon. I would forthwith go to my Study and ſet down the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Name upon ſuch a Text, ſuch a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e write down all the obſervable and uſeful Truth, I could remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and particularly and eſpecially ſuch Truth which was brought new to my mind, whereof I had not heard nor read much before. And this I eſteemed to be as well, or rather a better way then writing down in the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſt whilſt I was writing down ſome, I ſhould let ſlip other things that were then ſpoken of. But after and amidſt all, there is nothing like unto <hi>Writing them in the fleſhy Tables of our hearts,</hi> and to get them <hi>Engraven into our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts,</hi> That it may remain and be remembred even as long as our ſelves ſhall remain, even until words and time ſhall be no longer. <hi>But his Mother kept all theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in her heart,</hi> Luk. 2. 51. And ſo if ye can keep the true ſayings of God in your hearts, and not ſuffer them to paſs through or ſlip out again: Saith Jeſus unto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Hearers, <hi>Let theſe ſayings ſink down into your Ears. The entrance of thy words giveth Light and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the ſimple.</hi> Now put all this together, where God hath given to any Creature or Miniſter of his, a Knowledge of his Word and Aſſiſtance of his Spirit; and he accordingly being inſtructed therein, <hi>brings out of his Treaſury things new and old,</hi> when theſe are brought out and Preached forth, if they have an <hi>Entrance, ſink down into their Ears,</hi> and further, They are kept <hi>and Pondered in the heart,</hi> ſo kept there that it ſhall not go from them, here is the comfort of our Labouring in the work of the Miniſtry, as alſo the benefit of your hearing. Can ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member any good and true ſayings, or Gracious words that proceeded out of ſuch a Miniſters mouth? This or that, he ſpoke and taught, whilſt he was yet among us. I would not require it of ye to remember my particular and exact words, but it is altogether as well, if ye carry away the ſence and what it was I drived at, or exhorted unto in ſuch a Sermon; as the drift and deſign of this my Sermon is, if ye would make a continuing and perſevering work of it,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152401:13"/> 
               <hi>Be not Ignorant of the Devices of Satan,</hi> and do never give way unto them. I ſay again, If ye would make a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing and perſevering work of it, Be not Ignorant of the Devices of Satan, and eſpecially, Be not Ignorant of this one particular device of his. <hi>Where the word is ſown, when they have heard Satan cometh immediately, and taketh away the word that was ſown in their hearts.</hi> Now ye are not Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of this device of his, ſee well to it, <hi>Leaſt Satan get an advantage over you,</hi> in this particular and in this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Let him not take away the word that was ſown in your hearts at this Seaſon; for ye may prevent and help it if ye will. That is, if ye keep thoſe ſayings in your hearts which ye have heard uttered unto your Ears. And ſo it is of all his other Devices, they may be Countermined and Rendred of none effect.</p>
            <p>Whither it was that the Infernal Spirit did ſee and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, that I was to lay open his Devices herein; But I have obſerved, that I have been more let and hindred; I have been more untoward and unapt towards the Compil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Sermon then of others; which yet by the Grace and help of God is brought on thus far: I have obſerved much hereof, in my Contemplation and Searching out of Divine Truth, how many Avocations, Interruptions and Turnings aſide of my mind towards other things and little excuſes to leave of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or to go to other Buſineſs, have a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe and I have too often gave way unto it. Which is my ſin and I am to be blamed herein; and I believe that the Lord will ſhew himſelf diſpleaſed towards me for the ſame. When, <hi>He that hath ſet our Iniquities be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore him, and our ſecret ſins in the Light of his Countenance,</hi> Will reprove and ſet in order before me, the ſeveral ſeaſons of time I have done thus. As alſo when I have miſpent too much of my Precious time: When I that know the worth of time, the ſliding away of time, the Irrecoverableneſs of time, do not improve it better and more then I have done. The Lord knows the Reaſon of <hi>my neglecting the Word of God to ſerve Tables,</hi> Acts 6. 2. To ſerve the mean neceſſities of this Life, whereas all things relating to that ſhould be brought ready to my hand, that I ſhould not miſ-employ the leaſt Portion of my time, either for Food or Raiment, or neceſſary expence. And ſo indeed it would be, if I were righteouſly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152401:13"/> and equally dealt withal; If of ſuch an Inheritance which God hath ſet out to ſuch a Famlly, a like Share and Portion was aſſigned to me, as is uſually unto others. Or if the ſame was ſupplyed or helped another way. My Conſcience doth accuſe me, of miſ-pending time about wordly things, or even re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating to this Body; Tho' yet I do not altogether ſo waſte and conſume it, neither in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies or Vanity, or uſeleſs things as do others. This is another Device of Satan, to miſ-pend Precious time, which we ſhould not give way unto, no, not for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute. <hi>For we ſhould not give Place by Subjection unto this Enemy of our Souls, no not for a moment,</hi> Nor yet for the leaſt matter; But withſtand the wiles of the Devil, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is to be blamed,</hi> In that it is a ſin and a fa ult, which he would have us conſent unto.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall I more ſay? The time would fail me to tell of all his devices and wiles: They do termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and tend to one of theſe two heads, to commit Sin, or omit Duty, to Practice Evil, or hinder Good, and by this you may know them. For whatever is of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that ſame is a device or wile of Satan; The ſame Rule holds and is to be obſerved towards them all, Be ſure not to give way unto them. I ſay again, to confirm and eſtabliſh this word, Be ſure not to give way unto the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of Satan, as each may know and perceive them in the ſecret and deep of his own heart. And ſo when we ſhould always keep cloſe unto the Lord God in our hearts, and have them always lifted up towards him, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Lord in our hearts; Here when the heart Roves and is far from God, or when it ſinks down to the Earth and becomes Earthly or Wordly, or Savours the things of the Fleſh and of Men, this again, and ſuch like is one of the Devices of Satan, which we are not to give way unto an hands breadth, but to ſtrive and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour againſt it as much as ever we can.</p>
            <p>When Satan ſtood at the right hand of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to reſiſt him, the Lord ſaid unto Satan: <hi>The Lord Rebuke thee O Satan, even the Lord that hath choſen</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>Rebuke thee, Is not this a Brand plucked out of the fire,</hi> Zech. 3. 1. 2. Even the Lord that hath choſen <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Rebuke thee; which is as much as to ſay, Inaſmuch as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignifies
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152401:14"/> his Church and People, that God will have his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and Servants, <hi>Maugre</hi> and Notwithſtanding all the Temptations or Devices of Satan, or the Devil. <hi>And I give unto them Eternal Life and they ſhall never Periſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any pluck them out of my hand. My Father which gave them me is greater then all, and none is able to pluck them out of my Fathers hand,</hi> John 10. 29, 30. Not all the Men upon Earth, nor yet the ſtrongeſt Devil in Hell. This is a mighty Word of Conſolation and Aſſurance to all Real and Univerſal Chriſtians, who are within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Satan may diſturb, but he ſhall never be able to deſtroy ye. Tho' <hi>David</hi> did ſay through Ignorance, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity and Diſtruſt, I ſhall fall one day by the hands of <hi>Saul,</hi> but the Lord knoweth them that are his, and I cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify and aſſure all ſuch from the Word of Truth, that they ſhall never be devoured by this Roaring Lion. Tho' the Wicked and Ungodly, and Sinners may be Snared and broken, and taken, but this is the Priviledge of the Saints and Servants of the Lord, they ſhall never fall ſo far into the Snare of the Devil, but they ſhall be retrieved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered out of it again. Tho' here it will be convenient amidſt all his Aſſaults, to lift up ones heart in that Ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory Prayer, <hi>The Lord Rebuke thee, O Satan,</hi> the Lord Rebuke thee; or get <hi>behind me Satan,</hi> or ſuch like. I te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify and warn ye again, Be ſure never to conſent, yeild, nor give way unto his Devices.</p>
            <p>Thus having Diſcourſed of what excellent benefit and uſe, it is not to be Ignorant of the Devices of Satan, and having laid down that Caution and Rule, Be ſure not to give way unto them, and then He can never get advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over us; It remains to ſhew in few Words, How, the not being Ignorant of the Devices of Satan helps to make a continuing and perſevering work of it. This ye may quickly perceive and diſcern, for oppoſite unto continuing and perſevering, is Apoſtacy and Falling away. Now the Devil was the firſt and great Apoſtate; and himſelf having fallen into that Tranſgreſſion, It hath been his continued buſineſs ever ſince to tempt the Children of Men, to fall off from God in like manner. <hi>How art thou fallen from Heaven, O</hi> Lucifer, <hi>Son of the Morning?</hi> Iſa. 14. 12. Which tho' it be ſpoken there in reference to the King of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152401:14"/> 
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet it hath alluſion unto this fall of the Devil from Heaven. But we Read yet more clearly concerning that matter in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4 and <hi>Jude 6. God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to Hell</hi> (which doth ſuppoſe that it was from Heaven) <hi>and delivered them to chains of darkneſs to be reſerved unto Judgment. And the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels which kept not their firſt Eſtate, but left their own Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he hath reſerved in everlaſting Chains under darkneſs, unto the Judgment of the Great day.</hi> So that there is more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils then one, altho' one is <hi>Belzebub</hi> the Prince of the Devils, and is called the Devil or Satan, by way of Preeminency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is chief among them. Hence we ſee that their fault was ſinning and not <hi>keeping their firſt Eſtate.</hi> And God having thus puniſhed them for it, they are of the like Envious and Devilliſh Nature, as to tempt, ſeduce and deceive the Children of Men unto the like things, even to ſinning and not keeping their firſt Eſtate, which was Innocency and Uprightneſs. <hi>He that committeth ſin is of the Devil; for the Devil ſinneth from the beginning,</hi> 1 John 3. 8. And as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, all his devices tend to this, either in ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Families or Nations, or Generations of Mankind, where they come ſhort of what God hath required of that pure and undefiled, Sincere and Univerſal Religion, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath an hand in it one way or another; and ſo he hath in all the ungodlineſs that is in all People, here ſome of his devices take effect: So that it is of mighty conſequence not to be Ignorant of them.</p>
            <p>Every Act of ſin is a Part of Apoſtacy and Falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and it is as contrary to the continuing in the fear of the Lord, as darkneſs is unto Light. So that wouldſt thou continue in the fear of the Lord, the conſequent is, <hi>ſin not,</hi> neither <hi>Give place to the Devil.</hi> We underſtand likewiſe from hence how dangerous a thing it is, not to keep ones firſt Eſtate. For this was the miſcarriage and utter ruine of thoſe faln and accurſed Spirits; and through their means and temptation Man had very near ſplit Eternally and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverſibly on the ſame Rock, as appears by our Forefather <hi>Adam.</hi> But that God was pleaſed (more out of his Grace then our deſerving) to eſtabliſh another and ſecond Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, by which he is ſet up once again, by Chriſt, to try him once more. But wo unto him if he ſhall then fall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152401:15"/> and break the Terms and Conditions even of the Goſpel Indenture. Let People do never ſo many good things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>I know thy Works and thy Labour, and thy Patience, and how thou canſt not bear them which are Evil; and haſt born, and haſt Patience, and for my Names ſake haſt labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and haſt not fainted.</hi> (All this is well, and here is a good Character; but what ſucceeds?) <hi>Nevertheleſs I have ſomewhat againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt Love, Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen and repent, and do the firſt Works; or elſe I will come unto thee quickly and will remove thy Candleſtick out of his place except thou repent,</hi> Rev. 2. 2, 3, 4, 5. So that it is not a matter of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, nor of bare complaining to leave ones firſt Love, but indeed there is a real ground for Fear, and there muſt be labour to attain unto it again, and do the firſt works; Otherwiſe God here declares, that he will <hi>remove thy Candleſtick out of his place,</hi> That is, his Light and Grace from out of their hearts; and then in plain Terms there is no going to Heaven, the place of Eternal and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Light. Where any one leaves his firſt Love, this is one of their devices, and comes from thoſe formerly Angels but now Devils, who kept not their firſt Eſtate, but left their own Habitation.</p>
            <p>I teſtify again, unto all that ſhall hear or read this, Be upon your watch and ſee well to it, that this device of the Evil one doth not take effect upon ye; But rather thwart and contradict them the more. For this is to <hi>bear and to have Patience, and for my Names ſake haſt Laboured and haſt not fainted.</hi> When thou doſt ſo much the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, or contrary to his Temptations and Devices; for if thou art reſolutely given, it may be, Satan will be weary of tempting, or deviſing devices againſt thee.</p>
            <p>There is ſo much Reaſon that thou ſhouldſt not leave thy firſt Love, that there is all the Reaſon in the world to the contrary, that thou ſhouldſt <hi>keep unto thy firſt Love and thy firſt Eſtate,</hi> and rather encreaſe it more and more. Becauſe if you throw up a ſtone, It is obſerved that it moves quicker and faſter, the nearer it falls down again to the Earth: Which is its Center. So we being day after day nearer to Death and Immortality, and we draw conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually nearer in time, when we ſhall appear before God,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152401:15"/> unto whom all fleſh ſhall come, who is the father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and the Center of our Souls, and of all Created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>Therefore our latter and laſt days, ſhould be our better and beſt days; Our latter and laſt works, ſhould be our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and beſt works.</hi> For ſaith the Holy Ghoſt in the place afore-mentioned, <hi>Repent and do the firſt works,</hi> Rev. 2. 5. <hi>I know thy Works and Service, and the laſt to be more then the firſt,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>But call to remembrance the former Days in which after ye were Illuminated.</hi> Recollect and rub up your memories. At what Age or Seaſon of Life, ye were in the very beſt mind and frame of Spirit towards the Lord God. Where is thy Zeal and thy Strength, and thy former dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence? <hi>The perpetual hills did bow,</hi> the liftings up of thy heart continually toward the Lord God, and thy bowings before him in thy Spirit; and all that good mind and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards God. <hi>Are they reſtrained?</hi> Thou muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin again and return back to that former State, and Labour to add to it yet Sevenfold in each particular, now towards the very cloſe and ſhutting up of thy Days. <hi>And</hi> Jehu <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered all the People together unto him, and ſaid unto them,</hi> Ahab <hi>ſerved</hi> Baal <hi>a little, but</hi> Jehu <hi>ſhall ſerve him much: But</hi> Jehu <hi>did it in ſubtilty to the intent that he might deſtroy the Worſhippers of</hi> Baal, 2 Kings 10. 18, 19. So O thou Man or Woman, purſue here the like Reaſoning, in my Youth, or ſuch a ſeaſon of Life I ſerved God a little, but now I will ſerve him much; and yet more, that I may be accepted of him at the laſt. We are confident I ſay, and willing rather to be abſent from the Body, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord. <hi>Wherefore we Labour, that whither Preſent or Abſent we may be accepted of him; for we muſt all appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in the Body, according to that he hath done, whither it be good or bad,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 8, 9, 10. Knowing then, that we approach nearer and nearer to this, the right Exhortation and Inſtruction Prompts to do more Good, and to abſtain from all appearance of Evil. And as <hi>Jehu</hi> did utter that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying afore-mentioned, <hi>In Subtilty to the intent that he might deſtroy the Worſhippers of</hi> Baal. So do thou take up the like reſolution in good earneſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hitherto I have ſerved him a little, but now I will ſerve him much. And thou mayeſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152401:16"/> do it in ſubtilty alſo to the intent (for ſo thou mayeſt by the Knowledge and Grace given unto thee) to be more ſubtle then the Old Serpent, who is more ſubtle then any Beaſt of the Field; Be more cunning, or rather more wiſe then the Devil himſelf, as to render all his devices of none effect, to deſtroy and Root out thoſe Luſts and Carnal Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in our Members, which hitherto have Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that Infernal <hi>Baal,</hi> more then our Members and Body did Worſhip the God of <hi>Iſrael. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here is the mind that hath Wiſdom,</hi> and it is Soul-ſaving Diſcretion to make his own devices fall back upon himſelf, that he ſhall loſe more then he thought to get thereby. It ſometimes ſo falls out, that even from the oppoſitions and reſiſtances of Satan we get more Ground; that the Light which he would ſeek to extinguiſh and put out, doth ſhine more Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, and is thereupon known more abroad, as when he <hi>ſhuts up the Saints in Priſon.</hi> And ſo <hi>Paul</hi> Witneſſed, <hi>That the things which happened unto me, have fallen out rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the furtherance of the Goſpel: So that my Bonds in Chriſt are manifeſt in all the Palace, and in all other Places. And many Brethren of the Lord waxing confident in my Bonds, are much more bold to ſpeak the word without fear,</hi> Phil. 1. 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is in other Caſes, for <hi>the Delivery up into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons turns for a greater Teſtimony,</hi> according to <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 12, 13. if it be for Chriſt's ſake, or for the Word of God. And ſo it may be in leſſer matters, relating im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to the Souls of ſingle perſons. Even the Temptations and Devices of Satan may be over-ruled and ordered, as to fall out rather unto the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their own Salvation. I ſpeak Myſteries and Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs, as unto Natural Men, but the thing is certain and true. As on the one hand, the Spider ſucks poyſon out of the moſt wholſom Herbs, and the ſweeteſt Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; The wicked, and ſinners do draw Evil from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the Ordinances of Religion, and the beſt of things: So on the other hand, the Godly, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and the Wiſe, can, and do extract Good even from the poyſon of Satan, which is his Temptations and Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. As it is written of <hi>cauſing the Reproach offered by him to ceaſe, and to turn his own Reproach upon him,</hi> Dan. 11.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152401:16"/> 18. So they can even anſwer the Temptation of Satan, and ſo even turn that Temptation upon him, as to make the very ſame an Argument and Perſwaſion for God and Duty. A Notable Example and Inſtance we have of this in Chriſt being <hi>tempted of the Devil, Luke</hi> 4. 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 9, 10. Whereby Chriſt did Eminently ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ſtronger than he; for when he came upon him, <hi>He overcame him, and took away from him all his Armour, wherein he truſted,</hi> Luke 11. 22. <hi>For in that he himſelf hath ſuffered being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi> And as he is able, ſo he accordingly doth to all his Elect and Choſen Ones, and Faithful Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to the World's End. <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> And he gives them a proportionable Knowledge to anſwer and overcome the Temptations of the Evil One. He continually inſpires into the Hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Thoughts of Good to defeat the Suggeſtions of Evil.</p>
            <p>There is no Reaſon why any one ſhould not keep his Firſt Eſtate, or leave his firſt Love. Have a care of that. He that deſpiſes ſmall things, ſhall fall by little and little. The leaſt ſin is like a ſpark of Fire in a Thatch. We know not how far it will go, and how great a matter it will kindle. The beſt and ſureſt way is to put it clean out, and extingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. To <hi>daſh the little ones againſt the Stones, and to cruſh the Cockatrice Eggs;</hi> Even to mortifie thoſe Beginnings and Tendencies to luſt that are in our Members, To come up to that Eſtate which may be done, <hi>As for our Tranſgreſſions thou ſhalt purge them away,</hi> Pſal. 6. 5, 3. As an healthful and ſound Body may be Purged from Corrupt Humours. Stop, and prevent the firſt beginnings; for as he who makes Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to keep from ſecret faults and from ſecret ſins, will much more from thoſe which are more open and manifeſt. He that in the fear of the Lord abſtains from little ſins, he will much more abſtain from thoſe that are greater: So by the like Analogy and Reaſon of things, (for the ſame or like Reaſon runs throughout all the things of God; He that is not Ignorant of the Devices of Satan, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſort they be great or ſmall; He that doth not give way unto them in the leaſt, nor yet in any Inſtance whatever <hi>(Leaſt Satan get an advantage over us)</hi> as he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152401:17"/> would if the leaſt were conſented unto; In all Probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Likelihood, yea, in abſolute certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and aſſurance, he will make a continuing and perſevering work of it.</p>
            <p>And may the Lord God, who is a <hi>Sun and a Shield</hi> (in oppoſition to the darkneſs of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy) give us <hi>Grace and Glory.</hi> (We may and ought to pray unto him in his own order, according as he hath promiſed) <hi>No good thing will. He withold from him that walketh uprightly.</hi> May he give us that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Knowledge of the Devices of Satan the Enemy, and that Grace and Strength, that we may not give way unto him in the leaſt: <hi>So we may be confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a Good Work in us, will perform it until the Day of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>O Lord of Hoſts, Bleſſed is the Man that truſteth in thee.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Written by <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Ralph Simpſon,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Harp</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152401:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
